Hello, I'm your host David Bernard and
with me today, Revenue Cat CEO Jacobing.
Our guest today is Matias Gradel Norvig,
the CEO of Cybo, the game studio behind
Subway Surfers, the most downloaded
mobile game of all time with over 4.5
billion lifetime downloads. On the
podcast, we talked with Matias about
building the Subway Surfers marketing
machine on salaries, not ad spend.
leaving money on the table to protect
player experience and why more apps
should try rewarded ads, season passes,
and other tactics from gaming. Hey,
Matias, thanks so much for joining us on
the podcast today.
>> Hey guys, I'm happy to join.
>> And Jacob, nice to have you as well.
>> I'm I'm here. Let's talk subway surfers
games.
>> Yes, two CEOs on the podcast. These are
always fun for me getting to be a fly on
the wall. If it happens like usual, I'll
sideline David and just ask you a bunch
of tactical questions for my own for my
own education, but I I'll try not to
today.
>> Awesome. So, I want to kick things off
with the longevity of Subway Surfers. I
think everybody, you know, in our
audience will know what Subway Surfers
is, so we don't need to talk about that
specifically, but it is very unique in
how long it's been popular. I mean, I
think you just celebrated 4.5 billion
downloads, which is just insane. And so
I'd love to hear from you, you know,
what you think has contributed to that.
I mean, this this is what all
subscription apps would love to have,
you know, an all trails kind of thing
where decades dualingo, you know, you
want to be this like long lived, you
know, keep subscribers for a long time,
keep people active. Uh, so I think
there's a lot to learn from the
longevity of Subway Surfers.
>> Yeah, I think we um we came at the right
time. There was definitely both a timing
aspect where Bod and Sylvester saw the
the need for a next generation runner.
So, Temple Run came out and and designed
the genre, but Sylvester and Bodhi
perfected it. So, we can see that not
only our 4.5 billion downloads and of
course half of those are reinstalls
approximately. we could see that their
formula of the threelane mechanics, the
swipes, the curvy sort of left leaning
horizon,
>> uh, all those things have become the
formula for all other runners. So, I
think combined more than 15 billion
downloads uh, on that formula.
>> And I think, you know, in in recent
years, you can't hardly get on Tik Tok
without seeing Subway Surfers be uh,
part of these viral Tik Toks. um ho how
has that played into and what other
strategies have you worked on over the
years to to kind of keep it fresh and
relevant? I think early on the guys came
up with the world tour which was a way
of every 3 weeks going to a new part of
the world and inspiring people either to
see their own hometown or a nearby town
or a part of the world they hadn't
traveled to. So I think that helped us
keep fresh and then I think the
intuitive gameplay means that new
players coming in because you have to
imagine that in 2012 this was a game
from adults to adults but then everyone
that have started playing since also
play subway servers. So now we we know
that also a lot of kids are playing the
game but it was never designed for them
and it was it's just a product of a
really good and intuitive game that can
also be played by everybody. it starts
capping off at 4550 then people think it
gets a bit too twitchy and a bit too
sort of hard to uh to move the fingers
um not judging but I think overall we've
been able to to stay evergreen first and
foremost I think we we are in that
bracket of Angry Bird Subway Surface
Candy Crush all from the Nordics funnily
enough and then I think we um the
founders very early on said it's about
longevity we want to be a truly
free-to-play app where you can play the
core run as much as you want. We will
never pinch you. We we will never guard
you from content. Anything is achievable
through playing. And then I think that
as you say with Tik Tok, we've become a
cultural phenomenon as well. So, we can
see that when uh Jimmy Fallon mentions
us on tonight's show as an example of
how you make sludge content, when uh
Justin Bieber tweets us or the last week
tonight John Oliver mentions us, that
those are things that other companies
would would pay for and we're having the
luxury of being mentioned because they
think that this is how you do Tik Tok or
this is how you work on verity, right?
>> How have y'all leaned into that aspect
of things? I believe I've read that
you've made it very clear that folks can
use your IP in video and you're not
going to come after them and things like
that, but are there any other ways
you've leaned into that virality?
So, we've always had a strategy of
producing content that could be used for
UGC. So, every user generated asset is
also amplified if we think it's cool.
So, not only do we allow them to do it,
we also share it afterwards if they do
something cool. The team is also very
autonomous. So we've had a very
proactive team for many years that have
managed to make several viral waves
where we could see that the audience
really is picking up. But I think in my
12 years running this studio, I came the
year after launch, I have said no to the
marketing team twice
and they produce what five five 10
assets a day. So uh there has been very
few instances where I said maybe this is
this is too much.
>> There's often very little downside to
it, right? like you just if something's
bad, it often just doesn't go anywhere
and nobody sees it anyway, right? So,
>> yeah, that's that's also why I I like
what they're doing. A cool example was
we had Ramy, the Hall of Famer, uh who
also happens to be the keyboard player
of Foo Fighters, produced the soundtrack
for one of our cities. And um I had
agreed with him that look, we used this
picture and we know how cool you are as
a musician. We're super honored that you
wanted to jam with our in-house audio
designer. But then the team said, "Oh,
we also want to make this video." And
sends a a video that I didn't know how
would land with Ramy. So sending a text
to someone saying, "Look, I know my team
is super creative, but I don't want to
step on anyone's toes and I admire all
the creative work you've done, and I
don't want to come off as overly sassy
by sending something that just pisses
anyone off." Thankfully, he loved it.
But sending a video where you're not
really sure was meeting the two worlds
of our professional partners and the
in-house creativity. That was one of the
more fun texts I've had to send in the
last month.
>> You said in-house answers my question,
but is is all of your like ad creative
and sort of marketing creative done
inhouse.
>> Yes, it's basically um a content
flywheel like a furnace just spitting
out things. They brainstorm. They
remember to keep a balance of in-game
relevant material, which means that we
don't want just to create virality and
then people don't know where it comes
from. Some of the viral videos we did in
the past basically was just the team
having fun, which generated 100 million
views on a video, but people didn't know
that this had anything to do with Subway
Surfers. It still helps us with the
algorithms because of course they can
see which account it comes from and they
know that that account is tying to this
thing. So when I speak to Apple and
Google, they also acknowledge that part
of the algorithm is of course also
seeing what works on other platforms. So
if our content works on Tik Tok, we're
also featured more on on our app stores.
But the gameplay relevant material is
still very important so people see the
game and know don't just associate us
with being funny viral. The other
content is basically just riffing off of
everything that's coming. So whenever a
TV series goes global, we also did the
honey cake from uh Squid Games as a
subway surface logo, we do The Last of
Us, then we do a take with our
characters and we constantly try and
when I say we, I mean the team to just
ride the waves of virality because we
are one of them. We also have a swing at
the Dualingo every now and then. They
have a swing house.
>> I was going to mention it's very similar
to Dualingo's kind of strategy, right?
Of course it's in house. I kind of think
I knew the answer to that because you
just can't outsourced creative agencies
can't take risks with the brand like you
know it's just it's there's no incentive
for them to do it right and and it's
just very difficult if they don't have
buy in from whoever the this key brand
stakeholder is.
>> We had a new person joining the team. We
just bought the mascot costume for for
God that chases you in the game
>> and she did a dance with that costume
and I don't know if it was her very
first video but basically one of the
first videos she produced had 75 million
views. Jeez.
>> And that's a really tough that's a
really tough start to beat because of
course everyone was like, "Oh, make one
more."
>> Yeah.
>> Then fair fair to say she could say make
another game. It's super hard to make
success.
>> Yeah. Much much like games content for
games is a hits driven business, right?
Like it's hard to it's hard to get
lightning in a bottle twice, you know?
>> Exactly.
>> What does that look like on the paid
side and how has that evolved over the
years? Like are are you putting money
behind these UGC things? Are you paying
for brand? Are you doing like playable
ads and things like that? Like what's
the the paid strategy behind the kind of
brand and content flywheel?
>> The the short answer is that we spend
nothing. We spend salaries. So it's all
organic,
>> but it's also fair to say that we use
very small budgets to boost things when
we see that they go viral. So we do
amplify it, but we're talking tens of
thousands of dollars. We're not talking
hundreds of thousands or millions of
dollars. We're we're doing it very
strategically. When we see that some
content picks up, then we might put a
few hundred dollars behind it
>> just to create like other opportunities
for it to go viral, right? Like
>> Exactly. So So it transcends different
platforms because of course if you see
it on one platform, then we see that
this content could perhaps ignite on
other places.
>> So bring it over to Instagram and then
spend on some ads to get it to go viral
on that platform as well. That makes
sense.
>> So but in general, the flywheel runs by
itself. It's simply just them producing
things and also Justin Bieber makes a
new album. They make a post where the
guard says that the Justin Bieber got me
a choke hold for his new album and then
he posts that and the the first thing
some media does is Justin Bieber hints
new collab coming and of course we just
sit tight and don't comment because it's
not our business to correct it. Who
knows? We want we would love to work
with Justin. you should just reach out
if you're listening to the podcast, but
>> it could be in the works. It's just a
very early stages, you know.
>> Exactly. I mean, we we're up we're up to
play, but but it's just to say that
those things also live in a world that
is somehow out of our control where just
the fact that we are viral gives us the
ability to serve more content, but we
also really have to protect the brand so
we don't end up just becoming fat sounds
and whatever is trending that month. So
we we didn't go all in on Skippy toilet
even though quite a few brands did.
Right.
>> Is there one person there that is the is
the arbiter of when fart sounds is too
much. Is it sort of like in the culture
like who's who's guarding against that
like you know jumping the shark?
>> We have a couple. So I'm I'm probably
the ultimate pun intended. I'm the
ultimate boss to beat if you want to get
through with fat sounds.
>> Um but but in general we Christian
running the team is doing a great job.
But I also know that he's passed with
both his his peers and Celia the our
head of PX play experience as well as
Adam who is currently our head of brand.
They're both doing a phenomenal job of
of saying this is on brand this is too
much. Yeah, it's it's tricky to get in a
world where people are allowed to take
risks, but then you don't but you also
need some some safeguards, but you don't
want u you don't want the extreme of
that which is everything has to be by
consensus, right? Because then you just
get really
>> and that's also why I think even if you
ask them Celia and Adam, I think they
would say we often we don't often say no
either. So it's not a vibe of of
approvals. It's much more let's
brainstorm. And then we see, for
example, Hypen from a K-pop band post a
video where he does the facial
expressions to the sounds in the game.
We've seen several content creators do
that. And again, people think, well, how
much did you pay? And it's simply just
that they think that this is a cool
content piece to make.
>> Mhm. It these brands really become self-
sustaining at some point. Like, think
about Nintendo or Mario or something
like that. Like, they don't have to pay
somebody to do like viral things with
with the the Mario IP, right? It really
does become and that sort of
self-sustaining. And I guess like
something you mentioned earlier, you're
not pinching people so hard. You almost
have to have this very efficient like
content creation engine like if you want
to not have to pinch people, right, to
make the game like playable and and a
great freeto-play experience.
>> It's also because I think the founders
originally didn't want to monetize at
all. M
>> they just wanted a game that kept
staying free and playable and therefore
that would generate money. Of course we
we have further ambitions now and the
industry has also matured. So that would
not be enough in the current climate but
we are definitely uh winning or gaining
from just being an evergreen and seeing
that we in the top downloads every year.
We are in top five. We have been since
launch. Every year there are a couple of
not every year we have also been number
one but in most years there are a couple
of positions that are taken by companies
paying. So that's currently Roblox and
Garina Freef Fire. They are above us and
they're paying for their traffic.
They're making a lot of money. All good.
Then you see the occasional the yearly
trend. So you had the Among Us, you had
the piano tiles 2. Then you had another
game that people remember very well from
that year, but they're out the next year
of top 10
>> and we're still third or fourth. And
that means that every year we're also
gaining because either the spenders will
stop spending or the one year peaks will
go out, but we are the evergreen that
that keeps giving.
>> It's much better to be in position three
not spending to be than to be in
position one or two and having to spend
a lot to be there, right? Like in terms
of like an a business, right, in which
your margins are and everything. It's a
much more enviable picture.
>> Plus, plus then we see that, for
example, in the Mario movie, not a lot
of people realize that they actually
also made a reference to us.
>> So, in the early scene where they flood
the sewers, the newscaster starts
explaining that this also affects the
subway surfing. And again, that's just a
little love from some writer that that
had fun saying that this is a game.
Let's let's give love to the industry.
And and we we like to do the same the
other way around. I love that you said,
you know, we don't spend much except for
on salaries because a lot of people, I
think, do confuse the kind of UGC and
organic, you know, go viral kind of
stuff. You're still spending on
marketing. You're just not spending on
paid the way we typically think of it,
but I would imagine you have a pretty
big team. So, you are spending quite a
bit on salaries and and have a big team
running this. How do how do you think
about balancing that and and how big you
grow the marketing team and that sort of
thing?
>> So marketing for us is several things.
There's both platform relations and and
growth and content and player support
and so forth. The core part producing
content is less than 10 people.
>> Wow. And
>> so they are super nimble and very
efficient at producing. And therefore I
still think that we have fair salaries.
But it's just to say that it's not
because we're then spending a full paid
marketing budget on 10 individuals they
are themselves growing with both the
creation ordinary process as well as the
virality training. We had a a really
great talent with us for several years
and when he left I remember thinking
that how much is in him as a creator
versus the strength of the brand or the
virality
>> and the team definitely had to sort of
readjust. Okay, these are these were
some of the ideas that he would bring.
what new ideas were are we bringing? We
managed the transition and of course
that's a nice feeling for me as a CEO
that we can that we can build on it
regardless, but it's definitely also
talent driven. So both the people that
have helped us along the way and those
that are helping us now are worth their
own weight and gold.
>> That's an incredible achievement with 10
folks on the
>> I don't think you can have much bigger
than that. You know, like on Madmen, Don
Draper didn't have 50 people in the room
helping him co-write. You know what I
mean? like you for creative processes
like that, it really goes sour the
bigger the the group. So,
>> well, I wanted to transition and and dig
into the monetization side of things and
apps I I feel like still have so much to
learn from from gaming. You know, we we
do have examples like Tinder with the
consumables and multiple subscription
tiers and things like that, but I still
feel like apps are behind on the
monetization curve from what mobile
gaming has done this past decade. I' I'd
love to dig into how you think about
monetization and then and then
especially I mean you know as you layer
on different levels of monetization I
know you have ads and then you know
in-game currency and multiple in-game
currencies and other AP offers and
there's a lot of complexity that have
been layered in there. So I'd love to
start just at a high level like when you
started monetizing like what was the
thought behind it and and how did that
evolve over time and then we can dig
into the specifics of the economics.
Very early on as I say the founders of
Cybo Sylvester and Bodhi believed in
having a very simple just pure game
experience and that if people kept
playing that they would watch some ads
and by watching ads it would pay the
bills. The discussions we had with the
publisher for the first eight years,
Kilu Games in Ous were much more on the
side of them saying, "Well, we could
also put in these these things, but they
also generally like the approach of a
truly free game that could monetize
through ads because we've been live
since 2012. It also means that we cannot
be as sophisticated as you see some of
the other games because that would
alienate a lot of the elder players that
basically just like the way the game
works today.
So we just this morning launched the
biggest mobile collab I think ever with
the Brawl Stars where Brawl Stars visit
visits subway surface and subway surface
visits Brawl Stars and that's one way
where we can say look you still have the
core run to yourself. It it follows the
environment of a Brawl Stars universe
but in in a month's time we will visit a
new city. But the game mode that we do
with Brawl Stars is a way of also seeing
how are the players actually engaging
with us both playing with other IPs as
well as trying out game modes that are
so clearly an event for a duration of
time to see if if that scares away
people. Do they stop playing the core
run? How are they engaging with a PVP
mechanic? And does that allow us to
monetize those players in a different
way than they are in the game? Because
subway service obviously is constructed
in a way where if you play for an hour
without dying and you shut down the app
when you die, then you don't then you
haven't paid anything for your
entertainment. And I think in the future
at some point we have to figure out what
do we do with that because that's unfair
to the players that die a lot that would
then see more ads because that they are
they would probably feel that the
experience is worth where those that
play five hours perfectly would actually
not contribute to paying the salaries of
those who who make the product. So, it's
a constant sort of balancing act of
saying, how do we entertain as many
players as possible with something as
available as possible, but also allow
those who want to spend time or want to
spend money to progress or get more
content to do so without the expense of
ruining the fund for the majority.
>> I I read an interview you did that
somewhere between 80 and 85% of revenue
still to this day comes from
advertising. Is that correct?
>> Yes.
>> Wow. So, it's a mix of interstitials and
rewarded videos.
>> How do you think about those rewarded
video? This is something I've wanted to
experiment with and I feel like I've
seen some subscription apps
experimenting with this, but it it's
such an interesting mechanic to allow
somebody to pay with their attention
versus paying with money. And it's
something that is very common in games.
Again, I can't think off the top of my
head any subscription apps that are
doing this, but how do you think about
that mechanic? And how do you think
about that mechanic not, you know,
breaking the game or alienating users
like you said, you kind of already
alluded to it that if you could play for
an hour and never see an ad that, you
know, maybe that's too much or 10
minutes or 5 minutes is too little. How
do you think about not completely
breaking the experience with those
rewarded ads and you know what maybe
subscription apps can learn from that? I
think the conversations we have around
monetization regards the fairness sort
of when is it fair to to require payment
and whether payment is then through a
reward video or a subscription or a
premium feature or an inapp purchase.
There is no right answer. Especially
when you have a player base like us of
between 150 million people every month.
We know that we're not talking to a
player persona. We're talking to all
types of players at all times in all
markets. And that means that for me,
what the ads allow us to do is to also
be available and support markets that
would not traditionally have
subscription apps or use inapp
purchases. So tier 2, tier three, where
most other big brands would not
advertise and therefore not have a lot
of downloads, we are still the most
downloaded game in those territories.
But specifically for the US and for tier
one for Europe and for the sort of
higher earning countries of course we
would like to be have a share of wallet
and to know that if you're paying in all
your other games and you think well it's
nice over here that it's free we would
love to share with you the characters or
the unlocks that would sort of convert
you and share take part of the the
salary payments here and the sort of the
business of cyber. So from that point of
view, it is definitely an ongoing
conversation. Where do we have the the
real estate on screen to show a banner
or launch a reward video? And where do
we actually allow if you've spent money
in the game to remove some of the
interstitials and whether that should be
permanently or whether that should only
be for a period of time to say, well, if
you paid then you won't have any
distractions that you haven't chosen
yourself. And those those types of
balancing acts are are ever ongoing.
>> You you use the word fair, which is I
think what um a lot of developers do
implicitly when they're thinking of
pricing. They're trying to be like,
okay, what is a fair price? In this
case, you're not talking about dollars
for software. You're talking about like
attention in exchange for software as
well as like blending that into dollars,
right? Um which is really
>> challenging, right? I think this is and
one of the reasons that you know app
developers have avoided this. I think
one is the market has not been sort of
primed for it versus gaming. It's been
like this since as long as mobile gaming
is a thing. It's just it's complicated,
right? It's complicated to blend, you
know, you have an ad network and there's
a third party driving that and then
you're figuring out how it fits into
your experience and then and then of
course you have your own monetization.
Something you mentioned it kind of
highlights how challenging this is is
like you know only showing ads to
somebody when they die. Probably your
best and most engaged and maybe the most
likely to pay people are the ones who
don't die, right? So you've you've
actually like completely blocked off
monetization from them, right? So yeah,
you have to figure out what what you
know how can and what what can we sell
them? And then you know to some degree
another thing they bring to you which
not necessarily their attention but it's
their word of mouth, right? And so if
you're extracting from them, are they
going to be as likely to share you on
TikTok and get you your next, you know,
10 users, right?
>> And we still have 13 years in, we still
have a million daily new installs. And
as I say, half of those are reinstalls.
But that means that it's also worth for
us to keep the the content furnace and
the virality going and not jeopardize it
by trying to extract too much value.
>> Mhm. I think that's that's part of the
the discussion we have is that okay with
these feature we can try these these new
mechanics with the core run we want to
keep it clean but then of course we see
more and more game companies saying well
now you need a a short break from the
game we'll show you an ad and that helps
pay for the business that's that serves
this game to you I actually think that's
fair as well I have a a 9-year-old son
myself when he watches an ad I'm also
explaining him that this is the way that
we pay for that game Entertainment is
business. No one no one goes to the
cinema and doesn't expect to pay. So uh
so the fact that ads came in and I know
that that annoys some people the the
premium segment that just would like a
core experience from the storydriven
sort of a toz that's fine fine by me. I
like the fact that in in mobile gaming
you can actually play a lot of games
without spending and you use a part of
your time to watch games. And then the
playable ads are now so fun that people
actually also sometimes got just get
stuck in playing a a quick level of some
other game trying to advertise ours
right.
>> I I got stuck in that loop yesterday. I
I was playing Subway Surfers, you know,
knowing we were going to talk today and
uh one of the playable ads was so fun. I
spent probably five minutes playing the
playable ad and then uh then came back
to the game. But I I'm glad you brought
up your your nine-year-old son. How do
you think about protecting your brand in
the ads that you serve? You know, I I
had a a premium weather app. And I ended
up removing ads because I was having so
much trouble filtering. I would get
comments, you know, bad reviews on the
app store, emails to support saying, you
know, why are you showing ads for guns?
And I'm like, what the heck? And I'm
going into Google, you know, AdWords and
like trying to turn off like all the
like make it as, you know, age
appropriate as possible. And then I'd
get another one like, why are you doing
gambling ads? because it would have like
the slot machine ads and I go and try
and figure out how to turn that off. So,
h how do you approach keeping those ads
kind of brand safe and and kid safe and
so many kids are playing the game? So,
we're doing two things. And now it gets
a little technical, but obviously when
you install the game, you show your age
and if you are younger than the legal
age in your country, then you get placed
in what we call the copper segment.
Depending on the country, it's 16 or 13.
And if you're in the copper group, then
you are only served copper ads. And it's
only certain ad networks that that have
copper groups. So they they are not
showing anything that would not be
copper compliance. But even in the adult
uh version, if you say that you're older
than that age, and I'm I'm saying you
can still not you should not be able to
see ads for gambling, for guns, for uh
pornography, for anything that is
Rrated. And that's because we don't
believe that that's the way we should be
making business. When I say should not,
it's because of course the ad networks
sometimes make mistakes. And when you're
a shower of a billion impressions a
month as we are, then of course I'm sure
the viewers of your podcast could could
come with an example of well once I saw
this ad and uh and we would we would
actually actively go into the ad network
and say this is a mistake remove this
because we we have heard from a player
that this ad was shown. That's not how
we want to make our money. So we are
also very um proactive in the in the
sense that we we've blacklisted a lot of
categories that should not be shown.
We've uh done all the copper compliance
and uh and GDPR compliance and then we
also make sure that if anyone says I was
shown this that we also flag that to the
ad networks.
>> Yeah, I was going to say you must have a
team that's just dedicated to well one
responding when a a customer writes but
then like figuring out what ad work ad
networks you are and aren't working with
and like you know what's your obviously
you know expectations for yield and
stuff like that but that must be a
substantial amount of of effort. It's a
very efficient system and we have very
few complaints. So, uh, so we're
actually not we're not a lot of people
doing it, but they do it really well.
>> And then I think because we also have
SDKs in the game that allows us to show
what ads were were they shown. Pipeline
that shows us that these were the ads
that people engaged the most with and
these are the ones that they didn't.
>> Are you saying this like outside of the
ad network's own analytics? You you all
are tracking to like what ads are
performing the best.
>> Basically, which ad is is prompted.
>> Okay. Yeah. Yeah, cuz they can be very
kind of blackboxy, right? Sometimes what
like how the auction resolves and all
this stuff.
>> Yeah, that was my problem. And then how
do you think about
>> I mean you're a team of one, David. It's
it's challenging.
>> So it was so challenging. I just I just
gave up and pulled it out. Um but the
other the other thing I found really
fascinating, you know, as a weather app
developer, I download a ton of other
weather apps and check them out. One of
the fascinating things there is you will
see ads for other weather apps in most
weather apps. So, how do you think about
and prevent cannibalization? You know,
like me yesterday, I spent a minute or
two playing this other game that was
prompting me to go to the app store and
download that game instead of Subway
Surfers. And so how do you think about
that aspect of cannibalization that that
you may lose a player to this other game
that was advertised inside subway
servers?
>> I mean that's the business of freeto
play. So so we know that the cross
promotion or the the potential
cannibalization of an ad prompting you
to leave is a risk. We treasure the work
that the ad networks are doing to make
money for us. But of course, sometimes
they do it so well that we also see our
retention drop a bit because uh David
chooses to go into another game that he
finds more funny. Our confidence in our
product and also the also the longevity
that we're proven means that we are also
confident that you will come back that
you in your next PlayStation sit down
and and don't join join the game you
download necessarily but you remember
why you play Subway Surfers and why it's
one of the games that you remind
yourself of when you're in the subway in
the flying somewhere or in a bus with no
connectivity then then you're like
that's the game that you open but it is
definitely a thing that we have had two
instances of very direct sort
competitive titles. Just when Subway
Surfers came out, Singer did a game
called Running with Friends, which was a
complete copy. It was a bull chasing you
in Pmplona instead of uh the guard. And
we were actually quite not afraid but
aware and concerned that what what does
this mean to Subway Surfers if one of
the big games come in and just sweeps
the market? But it wasn't as fun. So it
went away quite quickly because people
could tell that Subway Surfers and
Sylvester Bod had cracked something
about the tactility of the game and some
of the intuitive nature of it that
cannot just be copied page by page but
needs specific sort of metrics that we
that we keep as our secret source. And
then uh we have King came with um Crash
Bandicoot which we knew that they wanted
to make a runner that would monetize.
They had put one of the best teams on
it. The IP is known. the game looked
amazing and uh they did a very hard
monetization and we thought this is
interesting because of course we would
also like to do a runner that monetizes
and if they came in and took just half
of our downloads but made $2 per player
then then that should have been us,
right?
>> Mhm.
>> Um
>> it's a good experiment for you to watch,
right?
>> It was. Yeah. And and I mean we we
actually had the talk should we tell the
the ad networks that please don't show
ads for Crash Bandicoot because that's
probably the only game where we don't
want people to then get excited and
leave the game and then find something
that was then better designed for
monetization. Uh in the end we uh we
actually didn't do anything and it
turned out that again Subway Surfers is
just the gold standard of runner.
>> Crash Bandicoot is his IP. I kind of
think Subway Surfers might be a little
more relevant in 2025 but
>> that's true. That's you, that's not me.
But but just to say that that we're
super happy that that we are still the
the go-to runner. We we consider
ourselves the king of runners and of
course we we hope with future launches
that we have other types of uh runners
than just subway one.
>> Can I ask you, you talked about this uh
you just launched today this this promo
with uh uh Supercell and and Brawl
Stars. Yeah. I mean that's a classic
example of you're you can't play both
games at the same time, right? So I'm
assuming we won't get into too much
specifics, but like how long does a deal
like of that take and like how do you
think about approaching those and
working with other companies and stuff
like that?
>> The initial uh exploration for deals
like that usually start a year before
>> at least a year before. Um it starts
with high level concepting and sort of
these brands would be cool. We also did
it with Crossy Road. We've just done it
with eightball pool which is of course
part of the mini clip family. uh and we
have other ideas for the rest of year or
next year. The concepting is sometimes
challenging to explain because what is
concepting? Well, that's a guy throwing
ideas up on a whiteboard that eventually
sparks the interest of a partner that
says we want to do that with you. How do
we make it happen? Then you put
engineers and legal and everyone.
>> Do you just start sending them ideas or
do you like get to one of your creative
people, one of their creative people in
a room? Like what's the process? I carry
a lot of the outward bey uh so the
business development side um I attend
conferences I speak from stage the
mobile space is a relatively small
industry so we also know each other
>> and you're all in the same like five
countries so it's helpful
>> that helps too it's a short flight to
Finland but uh it's also from the
friendly atmosphere we don't consider
each other competitors because we want
people to enjoy games and if they're
playing my game they will also play
yours and they will come back to mine if
mine is still fun.
>> Yeah, it's much less of a uh a finite
set of customers like B2B can be, right?
Like there's there's only so many
companies in the world.
>> Even I think the weather app is actually
a good example because you might only be
using one weather app and then if you
really have a wedding or around birthday
then you might check two apps but you
have a a habit of only opening one once
a day to check which clothes you should
wear. where games is much more of a
fluid activity during the day. And if
you are going on the bus or the metro,
subway service is likely one of the
games that are open because you lose
connectivity sometimes. But if you sit
at home and you bring out the the
console, then we also know that we're
not people's primary game. We are the
game that they play in between the other
sessions because they spend money and
time in GTA or Call of Duty or Sims and
then they play subway servers before
falling asleep or because uh they have
bit time in between sessions, right? So
I think from that point of view we can
also allow things to be a bit more
freely and therefore back to your
question a year before when we start
pitching high level ideas it's not very
concrete and then as the teams start
working together of course it becomes
more and more concrete how willing are
we on each side to do something in our
own game or is it more of an activation
for the other title and with crossroad
it was a very sincere collaboration it
also has been with eightball pool in and
uh in Supercell because the teams on
both sides are excited to work with the
other IP and we see a huge overlap in
players that knows both titles and are
excited to see what does that look like
in the game I play. I also know the
other game and I also want to try that
out. So we think there is a lot of also
reactivation of players that would come
back just for the fun of it and see what
does that look like in the other game.
>> Are the deals like fairly standard? Is a
lot of time spent on like the business
economics of it or is there a pretty,
you know, standard understanding of
what's industry norm?
>> Actually, these these deals have been
pretty bad. So, we're we're exchanging
traffic. We're uh we're saying, look, if
if we send players your way and you send
players our way, then what you monetize
and what we monetize is different, but
it boosts both of our numbers. So, we
actually haven't made commitments to
each other other than delivery of of
quality,
>> kind of what you're going to do and and
whatnot. I guess it makes sense. you
kind of mentioned that both brands have
to work with each other. You almost have
to be somewhat co-equal, right? In sense
for it to be interesting for both
parties. I've always found that with
partnerships generally is that if the
parties aren't of somewhat equal size,
somebody gets crushed or somebody's
uninterested or it it's just very
difficult. No, not for any reason,
right? It just kind of happens that way.
>> We have a lot more downloads than Crossy
Road, but Crossy Road did an amazing
effort in their game to integrate Subway
Surfers. So, I know that they got a
bigger bump in their downloads than we
did in ours, but it didn't feel unfair.
And I think it actually also helped with
the virality of both games in the long
term that you just see games that love
each other and teams that love each
other.
>> Yeah.
>> Like just to get their IP and your IP is
is positive, right?
>> And with Brawl Star specifically, I know
that they make a higher LTV than we do,
but that's also their dayto-day. So,
it's not as if we're coming in and and
tripling their LTV, but they will
probably make more money per player than
we do also after this game. We we just
like that we can create something cool
together that is authentic and native to
the brand.
>> That's something I hope we see more of
in the subscription app space. Straa
just bought RUA and you know, when that
initially happened, when I saw the news,
I was like, "Oh, that makes a lot of
sense. they're just going to like
integrate the running features and what
makes Runna runa into Strava. But no, it
doesn't seem like that's the strategy at
all. They bought Runna and now are
pushing people back and forth between
the two apps and RUA is like a great
brand in of itself and they're working
together like that. In that case, it was
an acquisition. But I I I hope to see
more of this amongst those kinds of apps
where there's with that one, maybe there
was a little bit too much, you know,
conflict uh for them to not buy and
just, you know, do a partnership
>> or it might actually be easier depend,
you know, sometimes BD can be just
difficult, right? Maybe it's just easier
to buy the company.
>> It's a meeting of minds when we have
these meetings. Also, the partnerships
we haven't announced. It's just exciting
to see the creative teams getting
hitting it off together and then seeing
that what comes out excites people.
We've gotten a ton of love of people
saying, "Wow, we can't imagine you got
Brawl Stars." And we're getting the same
feedback from the from our Finnish
counterparts at Supercell saying people
saying, "We can't believe you got Subway
Service." So, so it's also just a
synergistic sort of one one plus one
equals three, right?
>> Yeah. I mean, they the music industry
figured this out a while ago, right? Is
that like just collabs help, right? If
you can get more names on a track, it
just almost only upside, right, to bring
in other people's fans and trade the
music back and forth. And
>> it is a similar economy. It's like an
attention. There's there's much more
elastic demand, I feel like, in
attention than in a lot of different
categories. And which is maybe why we
haven't seen it in apps so much because
like for utility, you're filling a niche
and like there maybe is only to your
point about weather apps, there maybe
only like room for one or two apps in
somebody's life. But as apps become
we're in this phase right now where apps
are just proliferating at an incredible
rate into more and more niches that
might become less true right as the
niches become more narrow then suddenly
like you can collaborate between
adjacent niches I think the hard part
will be
>> gaming is like a decade ahead of apps
it's kind of it's kind of wild right
just yeah like considering we kind of
both started at the same time I guess
like gaming maybe you could count the
Nokia days right as like a head start
but it always feels like we're apps are
just a little bit behind and we're still
figuring stuff out So maybe it's a good
thing to just look and see what y'all
are doing and expect that we'll be there
in a decade.
>> Gaming is uh has been at the forefront
of monetization since and I joined the
industry in 13. It's an amazing industry
to follow and of course sometimes people
also take it too far. Right now with
apps in general I think I see the trend
of of course subscription is the mo best
way to monetize. It also sometimes feels
annoying that in order to scan this
document then you have to keep
subscribing to some utility app and then
eventually of course Apple and Google
allows another app that is free to do
it. So the notes app allows you to scan
and lot of people know that. So they
still uh subscribe to some scanner app
because they had one one document they
had to send to the to the state right.
So I think there is a definitely also a
a longevity factor for apps especially
utility apps or apps that serves a
specific thing where I would as a payer
prefer to the premium model or a yearly
model that is more fair than right now
where you feel like everything is $100
>> for a year of using something that is
like yeah but then it means I cancel if
it was priced more friendly to the
consumer
then people would actually perhaps not
cancel it. That's the balancing act that
games because it's been so massive for
so many years and we have so many people
are players. It's also found its
equilibria in the different aspects of
this is what players are willing to
spend where I think apps for me in some
aspects I end up spending too much
because I have one day's need of
something
>> and there therefore I don't become a
user of other than the straas of the
world because you're a runner or because
you do these things. That's actually
where I wanted to take things next is
and again speaking of like being so far
ahead of the app industry, the idea of a
season pass in apps a and all the inapp
purchases and the rewarded ads like all
of this hybrid monetization. I I think
we will see the industry start to adopt
over time where hey you just need one
scan okay five bucks like just make it
happen and like you know you're done. or
uh slopes is we had the founder of that
on the podcast and he now does a season
pass. It's like hey if you want
>> a season pass, day pass, they do a bunch
of like buy as little as or as much as
you want, right?
>> But then they also have the to your
point they have this subscription for
people who are avid skiers and who are
going to go out six times a year or
whatever and and so they kind of, you
know, they're a good example of kind of
making this work however the user wants
to pay and how frequently they want.
>> That's the advantage games have though.
I mean like you all you start with a a
store, right? Like you don't start with
a single IP. You have a whole store and
like so adding like a little thing here
and slice there. It's just that there's
there's just from out of the gate games
always start with like a higher level of
sophistication on monetization which
makes this stuff easier and apps and
this is something like in our mission at
renan we're exploring now is like is
this is the reason this isn't in apps
related to that inherent complexity and
can we bring these tools to app
developers sooner so they I don't know
what's going to work but like you know
if we can remove the technical barrier
at least like that way to let people
experience as you were mentioning like
finding that equilibrium because like I
think apps in general eneral to your
point like have kind of left the the
premium user out in a lot of cases right
either have some like very heavily
admonetized thing which often don't work
very well right there's very few because
I think they also just don't generate as
much revenue as like a a good high paid
subscription app for the subscription
apps like it just doesn't generate as
much right it's harder to work ads in
and they haven't developed these like
sophisticated models so like I don't
know maybe there's maybe there's the
underlying difference in like demand
elasticity and amount of need for
utility versus like need for
entertainment. Maybe they'll always be
different, but I I I would almost
equally bet that that we might see these
things like converge.
>> Yeah. And my specific question around
that too is like how do you think about
the season pass and you know have you
explored the idea of subscriptions as
some apps are starting some games are
starting to do but yeah how do you think
about balancing all of that? What I
really like about, and this is actually
probably Supercell introducing the
season pass, at least the way we saw it
in in Clash Royale, what felt really
fair about it, and why I've spent a lot
of money on season passes in games, is
that I also know that I don't forget
about it and then I'm charged forever.
So, we all have these discoveries where
we realize we've been spending $100 more
than we wanted on something that we
haven't used since last March. And
that's an annoying feeling where the
season pass gives you a very clear
overview of these are the things you can
get in this period of time if you spent
this amount of money. And then it
requires you to engage with the app or
the the game in this case. And it
requires you to play to get to it, but
it unlocks a separate track of rewards.
And I think that's a really fair way of
saying h because when I think back to my
childhood days in the late 80s early 90s
and we didn't have a lot of devices my
parents couldn't afford but those things
that you then finally got your hands on
were obviously premium titles that were
paid and sometimes you would have spent
$60 $70 on a game that you didn't like
and now you can get a ton of hours of
entertainment out of $60 and $70. So, I
think even if you then spend $8 or $10
on a on a pass, that's a lot of
entertainment, if that unlocks a lot of
rewards in a game that you like. So, if
the trade is fair, if you feel that it's
transparent what you get for that, then
I actually really like the season pass
idea. And then of course if your app is
a utility or a thing that you either
need but for example when I'm when I'm
um I signed up for a marathon and I I
want to say it as many places as
possible so I will do the marathon but I
would love an app that said I will get
you to the marathon but I will not
charge you for two years after. If at
the end of that said, let me become an
annual subscriber, then I like that
transaction, but and I think back to the
scanning app, then sometimes you just
need one scan, but you have to sign up
for 800 croner or $100 uh to get that
one thing or a monthly thing that
reactivates and you forget about it. And
I think the season pass figuring out
what is the right duration of time. Is
this a one day do everything you want?
Is this a one week? This is in subway
surfers 3 weeks for this season or um in
most other apps a monthly thing that
happens and then you choose whether this
also is a month where you feel that this
is worth paying for. Well Matias it's
been so fun chatting with you. I feel
like we could chat another two hours.
Honestly been an absolute pleasure uh
having this conversation and again I
think so many things that subscription
apps and and the kind of productivity
side can learn from gaming and and I
think you you've demonstrated that
today. So so many great lessons. Uh but
anything else you wanted to share as we
wrap up?
>> I think it's been a really good
conversation and I appreciate the
question because it also makes me think
how how games are far in some areas but
also other areas where we can definitely
learn from apps and I'm happy to come
back another time to discuss another
hour. I think my main thing is just that
the monetization and the gamification
that term is sometimes broad used a bit
too widely is about figuring out how you
make the player journey or the user
journey as frictionless as possible with
a few friction points that that also
makes it clear that here you have the
value points if you want to to make
those decisions and I think uh in
general it's hard to make games so we're
not saying it's easy either I know it's
also hard to make apps but I encourage
everyone who has an idea to try it
because I really like the creativity
that's that comes when people uh become
entrepreneurial on on areas that can
help others.
>> Awesome. Well, thank you so much for
joining us today. This is a really fun
conversation.
>> Thank you.
>> Thanks so much for listening. If you
have a minute, please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player. You can
also stop by chat.subclub.com
to join our private community.
[Music]